soft engineering radio episode 122
interview with the unknow Stepanovich
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at s e - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
so ya know please introduce yourself our
listeners
my name is the honor Stepanovich I'm
professor at Vanderbilt University
Vanderbilt is in Nashville Tennessee I'm
director of the Institute of software
integrated systems Isis Isis is
University affiliated research
organization it's we have about 35
full-time researchers engineers 8
affiliated faculty and roughly 50
graduate student so it's it's the size
of Isis is relatively big relative to
usual academic measures my interest
research interest is in the design and
implementation of systems that are both
computational physical or they include
computational components and physical
components related to this on the
computational part our started working
in the last I mean over 20 years ago on
model-based design our take on
model-based design is called model
integrated computing or an IC
distributed real-time embedded systems
is a particular kind of computational
target right for modern integrated
computing but you know that you can do
model-based design for just about
anything
yes so that's one of the target platform
the distributed real-time embedded
system plans once yeah but we are very
heavily involved in in the system side
of the overall landscape control digital
signal processing adaptive systems and
I've did quite a bit of work in those
areas as well so in the material I I
used for preparing this interview you
talk about cyber physical systems
it sounds to me a little bit like the
new buzzword can you can you outline
what those systems are all about
indeed it sounds like a new buzzword
particularly if you compare it with
usually embedded systems or network
embedded systems the area but let's let
me just make a pitch for this new
technology so as you know many ways one
of the greatest ongoing transformational
technologies that networking computing
is more and more penetrating quite
deeply into physical systems in fact we
use these systems as a universal system
integrator these days that kind of deep
penetration of networking and computing
in large scale and even small-scale
engineered systems what we built is a
major revolution it is it started twenty
fifteen years ago and that's gradually
transforms whole industries it goes so
far that that these days if you look
engineered products in major areas like
avionics and others the computational
networking component quite a bit exceeds
50% as value-added now the the
traditional embedded systems view of
this area is let's see what the
physicality in the environment does to
computing specifically how we form the
acquirements how we software for these
systems what kind of network properties
we build but again the focus is what the
physicality the environment does to
computing but there's a very important
other side of this the other side of the
story what the embedded computing and
networking does to the engineers
ultimately that's what drives the whole
process
and cyber-physical systems try to
emphasize that what we are looking for a
system category which is so tightly
integrated that you cannot sort it out
what is the computational part what is
the physical part because both of this
side inherently needed to implement the
new properties so what we really want to
look in the cyber physical systems what
are these new properties what are the
new qualities that the integration of
physical and and computational objects
can bring there can bring in these
systems so that's what we mean by cyber
physical systems okay so before we look
at some of those properties and
challenges can you give us a couple of
maybe a little bit more detailed
examples of where these kinds of systems
show up you already mentioned I guess
avionics and improbably defense so so
can you give us an example so people can
imagine where this kind of stuff shows
up or is used what you would
traditionally call systems industries so
aerospace of course all aspects of
aerospace if you look at yon existence
flight control systems or just yeah you
lose you look modern airplanes they are
real example for cyber physical systems
they are they are the major industries
of course also motive industry if you
look the modern cars the electronic
content is tremendous and and the new
features but what embedded electronic
does to the cars to the dynamics the
drivability the energy efficiency of the
cars is huge but there are many others
industrial automation telecom health and
medical equipment so it's just about the
most pervasive transformation that costs
really across all major engineered
systems mmm-hmm
you talk about a specific design flow
that is relevant for cyber physical
systems can you can you give us some
details here but I would really advocate
here is that the design flaws when what
you use for building science
their physical systems are inherently
heterogeneous typically they cross or
they include three major disciplines of
course software and computing is one
general area but it also includes
control and systems engineering somehow
the design flaws are built as the
combination of these different kind of
engineering disciplines now the other
part of it is that design flows are
usually built such that that you have to
highly customize them to the needs of
the actual domain obviously design flow
for for engine control or drivetrain
control in cars is different and design
flows for process automation because the
nature of the system is different your
attention the optimization requirements
are highly different so if if there is
one thing which is common in all of
these design flaws that they have to be
highly flexible you have to be able to
define in the design flow specific
abstraction layers these abstraction
layers give a way to express your design
ideas implementation ideas were there
other layers and you compose the overall
flow along the usual step refinement
mapping across these different
abstraction layers and so what you're
doing here and and what's also probably
going to be part of your oops lucky note
is that you use the main specific
languages for modeling or designing the
systems on these different levels right
yes
actually is a is a very interesting
phenomena that that in these three
disciplines software control and systems
but I may also need to append here
security engineering which is becoming a
very important issue the different
domains or sub domains bring their own
engineering
disciplines and methods with them now
control engineering and systems
engineering has been traditionally
model-based that's that's how they
trained people that's how they think
that's what it will look like it's
interesting too if you go to get
together with control folks and they
talk about about models and then you
take some software person and also use
the term model those people mean
completely different things and often
have a hard time actually understanding
each other my girlfriend works in
control automation and if we talk about
model driven or model based we hardly
find the common understanding
but in the same time though the modeling
languages can be different yes but
really emerging that that because
modeling really gained tremendous weight
in software as well yeah that gives us
an opportunity to make a new synthesis
and basically in the in my oops what
keynote I really would like to focus on
this new synthesis the opportunity for
convergence that all of these great and
and indeed what I feel is that that
domain-specific languages and in just
the whole agenda of being able to look
from a higher level
what are these languages how can we
define them how can we compose them
gives us the opportunity for major
convergence across these areas and that
convergence is not done yet but but
certainly we understand more and more
how it could be done right yeah I agree
I'm as you know I also work in the in
the model of an area and I also always
talked about that in my trainings that
that you can also model hardware and
stuff with with modeling languages and
on model level software and hardware out
the same they're part of the same model
or set of models and as you say that
gives you a very new way of of seeing
all those things under the same well
meta meta concept or something yes
that's that's actually in our experience
it's is one of the concepts that are
hard to get through for for other these
the
the software folks are very easily
understand these different abstraction
layers and just the fact that the
abstraction itself can be the objective
of design you know in if you if you look
at the disciplines like traditional
electrical engineering the education is
built up in those areas such that
students are receiving as part of their
education they represent formed
abstraction layers down to the notations
yeah yeah and therefore it's deeply
ingrained that how I need to represent
and deal with let's see the linear
system dynamics or digital circuits
right this is this is told in one
package it never comes up that why would
I want to change the notation why would
I want to design new abstractions for
describing a new domain which is part of
the whole software and computing mindset
so that's that's really the interesting
interesting aspect of this whole synergy
which is evolving yeah an interesting
tangent here is maybe have you heard
about Shannon wings computational
thinking yes I think that's very
interesting idea or realization or
whatever to teach non computer
scientists you know abstraction state
based behavior and these kind of things
although they don't do software it's
still relevant for building systems yes
yes that's that's indeed a tremendous
opportunity and and frankly that that
convergence which is based on the cross
fertilization of these areas is a huge
promise yeah so I think that that that
type of computational serious thinking
where one element of it is that you that
you teach in other disciplines how you
formulate adjust mode eita modify your
abstraction is a very important idea
yeah
okay so um why don't you outline some of
the main challenges in building those
cyber-physical systems one of the most
important thing of course in all
engineering systems in composition
composition is our bread and butter to
manage complexity you know that
composition has two aspects of it one is
compositionality which means that the
properties can be computed from the
local system level properties can be
computed from the component and
composability which means that that the
components will not charge they change
their properties when you put them into
system but the of course is a very very
hard thing to do if you are building a
large interconnected systems that are
that are inherently heterogeneous yeah
what what we usually tend to do that in
order to manage complexity let's say
inside the physical system how would you
would do that well this is our tradition
usually we build software so there is a
software discipline which will design
the software architecture then we define
the control then divet and the systems
engineering part as separate the same as
if the other would not exist but they
are very exist of course because we are
designing exactly the same system there
are a whole lot of interactions and if
you stick strictly with with this
separation of concern idea these
interactions are not modeled you are
sitting happy in the in your modeling
world of control without considering
what the implementation the
computational components implementation
will do to you of your system dynamics
so resolving these issues how can i
reconstruct or develop theories for
composition in heterogeneous systems is
certainly one of the one of the major
challenge now
in another major area what really is
just inherently part of all model-based
design is that we use tools the
omaha-based design is driven by or opens
up the opportunity to do tool based
approaches so we engineer the system we
specified and we refine the models we
extend and we transform them and if you
look the design automation market and
where are we in design automation in
general or this kind of system category
but what you see is that of course
wherever you have a massive market which
provides stability and longevity for
developing high-value tools then those
tools are created and exist of course
VLSI design is a canonical example for
us where these high-value design
automation to change have been created
the situation is much much worse and
much messier insidious cyber-physical
system why because because there are so
many of them we need so many different
kind of flavors again as we were talking
about it earlier what you need design
flaws and related to change in
automotive might be quite a bit
different from the to change what you
need for embedded sensor networks or for
avionics systems do you think that that
sysml is a is a you know viable standard
to create this bigger market so that
good tools can emerge or is sysml has
the same problem as UML in that is too
generic yes so that's the problem that
if you if you want to buy out yourselves
from the need for flexibly creating and
customizing design flaws modeling
concepts and create these monolithic
large languages
then perhaps you can get a hope that you
recreate based on large sender standards
like the seasonal the environment for
this complicated design automation too
sweet but but I strongly believe that
that there will be always a variety that
the areas across the different
subdomains are I mean the difference is
so big that it will not allow it to
select one or the other less than that
over the as a dominant thing so it's not
like computer languages it's the
differences are essential so there is no
other way than just to understand how to
resolve the dichotomy how can how can i
beard in a very flexible way highly
customized design automation tools but
in the same time not lose reusability
that's that's basically the most
exciting technical challenge for this
area right I agree and in software it's
kind of the same thing I mean many
people say that UML is good enough for
everything but of course the whole DSL
advocates who just do software like the
meta headed folks are also myself they
strongly believe and know from
experience that more specific languages
are better so even in the software world
only I think this this this problem
exists yes yes yes indeed and it's
particularly essential in in this
cyber-physical system where
heterogeneity is really going very deep
and very far to other things you talk
about this certification and security
against the certification aspect is
probably especially relevant in in
avionics and other like high risk
environments right yes
certification of the cyber-physical
systems is is one of the one of the huge
challenge that the systems companies are
facing and as you know that as much of
the certification related standards are
really highly processed based
there is no such things that that
compositional certification usually if
you make any change in some aspect of
the system simply because of the lack of
compositionality in the overall system
design and because of the unmodeled
potential interactions across you have
to recertify the whole system and that
that needs to be resorts certification
of course is a major problem for the
avionics folks the aerospace industry
you know I'm sure that everyone heard
these this tremendous cost numbers how
much does it cost certifier a large
airplane it's billions and billions of
dollars and and really the if that issue
is not solved sooner or later just the
requirement and the cost of
certification will will be a huge
pushback yeah to beardy systems it's
it's even in like general aviation very
simple systems diamond who have a hard
time certifying their new diesel engines
it's no there is no there isn't much
cyber-physical systems involved it's
just certifying Hardware I guess if you
do cyber and software stuff it's way
more complicated even yes and of course
hand-in-hand with this come the whole
area of system integration and you know
the system integration these days is
that you build all of the components
hoping that at the end of the day we
just plug them together easily because
plug and pay and and create the complex
system and everything works but again
the problem is the many many on model
the interactions and the result is that
this whole one-shot system integration
which is focusing on delivering
components in the system integration
lads is just not scaling it's
uncontrollable that it's
very hard to predict what will be the
cost and usually the solution is that
people are just doing a system
integration by testing and testing and
testing until the money is running out
and and that of course costs and ruinous
quality and results in tremendously
expensive recalls you know automotive
industry and sinners so that that whole
issue has to be reconstructed and of
course they are new emerging very nice
techniques that are really that are
moral base that try to systematically
approach this try to do incremental so
you you pursue a an incremental concept
of system integration that small ways
have some version of the system which is
which is operating where you can shift
in and out parts of the system from only
models to real hard or your software in
the loop elements so there is a huge
transformation also what I see in the in
the whole system integration area yeah
so when you rupes like you know you're
probably going to outline those
challenges and and and maybe some
solutions right yes I I really planned
to talk about these challenges show
examples how this fundamental
transformation is going on and again
what what I'm really captured by that I
feel that that very interesting
convergence which is emerging across
these isolated disciplines and that has
very deep impacts not only how we do the
practice but how we teach engineering
and and as an academics who is involved
in in curriculum and and creating
courses and so forth that's also very
important a very important aspect of the
overall story okay then pianos thank you
very much for being on the oops la
podcast and I guess you did motivate
people to actually come to your keynote
which is one of the points of this
podcast thank you very much
thank you
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SE radio team via
the website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and slash dog
puppies to contact the team please send
email to team at s e - radio net or if
it is specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 licence please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the positive music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
travel
[Music]